let's go in Practical terms and kind of
ultimately all a person would need to do
really is
uh keep an eye on their own
intentions motivations what makes them
act cuz that's what
determines wholesome and un wholesome
and then how wholesome or how un
wholesome it can
be and that's something you cannot not
be aware of
of and mindfulness is the is something
you can't have too much of as the Buddha
would describe it's not like a Ric mean
describe it's not like a Ric mean
observation of moment to moment to
moment no it's awareness of that which
is already present fundamentally
intentions cuz if you're mindful
basically of the of your body being
you're mindful of your situation that's
already intentional if you're mindful of
your feelings you're mindful of the
situation that's already intentional
which means you are then
mindful not not necessarily to the full
extent that's what it would have said
mindfulness developed to the extent
necessary for the final
knowledge but the possibility of you
being mindful of it is always there
because these things are
present so that means you can actually
then discern the background of whatever
your situation is which is already that
background is part of it you can then
discern the the subtler motivation
behind your actions and if you if you
discern it you will see if it's
wholesome or un wholesome is this rooted
in in desire sensuality greed aversion
is this rooted really in your will
desire to harm or something or is
genuinely rooted in in uh in in in good
in non- greed non
aversion uh and if if once you discern
it you'll be able to then not act out of
it and that's all you need to do you
don't need to try to get rid of the
possibilities of unh
wholesome they're just part of how
things arise you can use it for good or
for bad responsibility is on your choice
how to use it not on the possibility of
how it can be
used but none of that can become
apparent if you're just sort of uh
completely if you have completely
obscured that responsibility of your own
choice that wholesome that UNH wholesome
and you obscured it through denying or
through projecting it on to someone else
someone else's fault it's it's the God's
Will and everything else
say even if it's God's will to present
you with a certain Choice he can't make
you choose this A over
B that's why the early existential
philosophy said it's not that that the
phenomen phenomenology and
phenomenological method it's it's
atheistic or anything like that it's
basically just recognizing the fact that
God has no power over your choice so you
can allow the gods to exist as much as
you want but none of the Gods can tell
you how to choose it you are the one who
chooses what what God told you to act
upon it which means whether the things
come your way out of complete
circumstance Randomness accident God's
will previous action previous Karma and
viac and whatever else makes no
difference cuz you presently are
responsible for choosing how to act upon
it oh this is because of no sorry I've
done this because of that no because you
done that because you chose this to be
the reason for it
you can always say no to everything or
yes to
everything which means you can always do
the the opposite of whatever it's
presented to you means the choice is
always on you that's why the whole
definition in the in the philosophy was
basically uh man is condemned to be
free which you you cannot not choose
like sometimes people think if I
abstained from choice I didn't choose
but abstain from Choice it's another
choice you just chose that and that's
why the Buddha said being means exactly
this basically beings are bound with
their actions they cannot Escape it as
in abstaining from your action becomes
an action for you so the only way to
escape the action is to truly first
accept it and then see the degree of
your responsibility in it and stop
maintaining that not trying to overly
deny action or overly explain it
sorry so in Practical terms if people
want to meditate and practice correctly
uh in this
manner always keep a corner of your eye
at the back of your mind basically where
your intentions are and before you do
something check with yourself why why
are you doing it why do you want to do
it you always get an
answer it might take a time to cut
through all that like like layers of
coverups but it's there you know the
truth yeah you know the
truth as we were discussing before the
similar I was telling you well the
example it wasn't really similar but
like say say you're somebody who who is
on a on a on
a oh that's a beautiful
eego you're somebody who is who's on a
on like a not necessarily a strict
Meditation Retreat but say you're
practicing seclusion practicing non-d
distraction and so and then you have a
thought that arises oh I want to go I
want to go to the to the to the
library in the in Monastery and now to
get some suta books so I can read and
study harder now I see on the external
based on the external point of view
that's a good thing to do reading sutas
enriching the basis of your knowledge
contemplation and so on
but that's not the point of view that
matters it's the internal point of view
that matters for whoever practices it so
what you should want to do not like try
to justify your impending action based
on the external acceptance of it or
denial of it you want to justify it or
not based on the internal reasoning so
if you start looking at it why do I
really want to go to the library and
take these books right
now wait for a while cuz probably you're
not going to get the answer immediately
but you you can then see that oh
actually I want to go because I hope
there'll be some people there and I'll
end up being distracted I'll end up
talking to somebody cuz I feel a bit
well a pressure of doing nothing being
alone so going into into the the the
group of people can alleviate that
pressure but I I can't admit that to
myself directly so I oh I find an excuse
of going to library to take the suit
where I know there's a 90% of chance
they will be like-minded people and
they're going to start talking to me but
that's the whole point then I won't feel
respons responsible for choosing to
distract myself because while they
started talking to me it would have been
rude to just remain
silent but you fail to see that you
already decided to talk to them by
making yourself liable to that
possibility of going in the environment
where there's a good likelihood of
people distracting you from your own
basically self-awareness and Solitude
and so
on so now you can say oh so I'll never
go to library again well that's also
impossible that's also trying to
overdoing it no go to the library but
for the right reasons there might be a
genuine need to go to the library but it
was the UNH wholesome part of your mind
that made it into the UNH wholesome
rooted it in UNH wholesome desire cuz
yes certain things you can abandon
straight away engagement in sensuality
sexuality lying stealing you abandon
that there is no wholesome way of doing
that but as the Buddha pointed out there
are things such as eating food you can't
stop that cuz you
die but if you eat it careless ly if
you're not aware of your reasons behind
eating the food if you don't keep those
reasons present and clear if you don't
develop Clarity in regard to them
inevitably you're going to eat out of uh
out of greed and out of sensuality out
of enjoyment for Taste not need for the
nutrients and that's something you have
to responsibly maintain each time you
eat the food and that's the whole point
of that contemplation I will eat for the
sake of uh health and sustenance of the
body strength so I can continue
practicing I will not eat for
beautification I will not eat for
sensual enjoyment I will not eat for
Taste but that's not something that's
always written like decided for you
that's something that you choose to
decide every time you go to eat food so
in this particular instance all you need
to do is be careless of you eating the
food and immediately become Central if
you're not careless it doesn't go into
sensuality but people that's that's
harder to maintain so it's much easier
to then just say I'll not eat food or
I'll only eat food that I hate and so on
that doesn't matter you're still going
to eat for UNH wholesome reasons then
cuz the UNH wholesomeness of eating food
for UNH wholesome reasons it's not in
the food it's in your carelessness so in
the example of going to the library no
you can still go to the library if you
really need to get the sutas or or other
books that might help you contemplate
further but then you do it very very
carefully go to the hours when you know
there won't be people if there are
people avoid looking at
them if you have to look at them avoid
talking to them even in the sake of
being r
and that's how you know you will not
give rise to the UN
wholesome but if you just say I'll never
step outside of my house I'm going to be
locked in this cell for 3 months I will
not talk to anybody ever again you're
just obscuring the problem you you
you're not going to see where the line
of your responsibility is why because
you're denying the whole
thing that's why the Buddha did make
actually it's an offense to to uh engage
in the practice of Silence not talking
to
anybody ever again cuz they were like
those athetic brah they would just
refuse to speak for the rest of their
life they said well it's
misguided but most people would just
jump on the first excuse oh why do I
need to go to library oh because to get
the suts and that's a good thing okay
fine while the real reason remains
underneath right there and but they
refuse to look at it because then it
will fill you with guilt anxiety sense
of responsibility which is already a
burden
and that's where the practice is I'm
doing that burden but in order too the
burden of responsibility first you need
to accept it not denight